Finding Aid for the June Wayne Papers LSC.0562
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1942-1997
  - Subseries 13: Tamarind Lithography Workshop and Tamarind Institute, 1956-1997
    - Lowry, McNeil 1- 4 5 Jan 70 - 22 Nov 70 FF 51c, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: grant and budget for Tamarind Institute; Wayne's resignation from board; Thomas Hoving committee; Sterling Institute lawsuit; Lev Mills; problems between Tamarind and Terry Sanders Company over film, "Homage to a Lithograph"; other correspondents include Allan J. Greenberg (attorney) to Lowry re Greenberg's work with Tamarind Lithography Workshop; Nancy Boggs to Wayne re slides of Tamarind exhibition at Ford Foundation; also includes copy of "A European Study Proposal In the Graphic Arts 1970-71 Academic Year" by Lev T. Mills.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-15 26 Jan 59 - 23 Dec 59 FF 85c, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 2)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: proposal for establishing a lithography workshop; Wayne's nomination for consideration in Ford Foundation's 1959 Program for Visual Artists; opinion of Lessing Rosenwald re establishing a lithography workshop; consideration of Marcel Durassier (master printer) to work with workshop in the United States; other correspondents include Wayne to Elie D'Humiere re importing lithography paper; Jules Langsner re evaluation of the proposal.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-14 6 Jan 60 - 26 Dec 60 FF 104c, 1960 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: commitment from Garo Z. Antreasian and Clinton Adams to Tamarind Workshop; assembling Panel of Selection and Board of Directors for Tamarind; Tamarind's tax exemption status; Power of Attorney document for Tamarind; Tamarind's initial budget; publicity for Tamarind grant announcement; Tamarind's first fellowship project and artist, Romas Viesulas, visiting New York with portfolio and prints.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-13 16 Jan 61 - 8 Dec 61 FF 54c, 1961 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: Tamarind budget and financial statement; Garo Z. Antreasian and Clinton Adams departing Tamarind; agreement for sale of Tamarind Impressions; Wayne and Clinton's reservations about the Print Submission Center; engaging Bohuslav Horak [aka "Bobisch" or "Bobish"] as printer at Tamarind; printer Joe Funk and investor, Peter Lehman, establishing Kanthos studio next to Tamarind; exhibition of Tamarind prints at UCLA; collaborative projects with Ray Bradbury and Michael Blankfort (screenwriter/novelist); Tamarind fellow Rube Kadish sudden departure; Adja Yunkers; Harold Keeler coming to Tamarind.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-16 FF 57c, 1961, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      Biographical introduction and transcript of W. McNeil Lowry's speech, "The University and the Creative Arts" given to the Association of Graduate Schools (New Orleans, 1961 October 24); transcript of Lowry's speech, "The Ford Foundation and the Creative Arts" (Los Angeles, 1962 January 10) for exhibition of Tamarind Lithography Workshop.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-12 31 Jan 62 - 13 Dec 62 FF 60c, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 6)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: Tamarind's tax exemption status; Frederick S. Wight (Director of the Art Galleries, UCLA) re exhibition in New York; engaging Calvin J. Goodman (Consulting Management & Industrial Engineer) to do study on the economics of the art of the lithograph, "The Fundamentals of the Operation of the Lithography Workshop"; Garo Z. Antreasian and John Herron Art Institute collaboration; William Brice as Associate Director of Tamarind and joining Board of Directors; three-year grant proposal for Tamarind; Bernard Reder (sculptor) as possible candidate for Tamarind work; Wayne's cash flow predictions for Tamarind; replacing Bohuslav Horak [aka "Bobisch" or "Bobish"] as printer at Tamarind.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-11 3 Jan 63 - 19 Dec 63 FF 92c, 1963 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: Rudd Brown and Bertha Lewinsohn visiting New York; Tamarind accounting and financial statement; memo on "Prints in Progress" program; proposal by Fritz Eichenberg (Art School, Pratt Institute) for Pratt Intaglio Center; Wayne's comments on UCLA Cultural Arts Festival; Durassier seminar; Harold E. Keeler and producing limited edition, original hand-printed monographs; Tamarind budget; Wayne request for fellowship for Rufino Tamayo; Tamarind annual report; catalogue by Egon Kornfeld of work by Sam Francis while at Tamarind, "Sam Francis -- Lithographs 1963"; Louise Nevelson re her grant and work at Tamarind.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1-11 3 Jan 64 - 10 Dec 64 FF 60c, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 8)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: publication, "Prize-Winning Graphics, 1963"; Jason Leese re his fellowship at Tamarind; lithography marketing study; Wayne's report on Tamarind and problems re availability of lithography stones, disposable aluminum plates, and paper; publication of study, "Marketing of the Original Print"; Wayne's request for extension of October (1965) termination of Tamarind Lithography Workshop; annual report; Ford Foundation news release re awards for the Foundation's Program for Administrative Interns and request for Wayne's nominations; Ford Foundation's Travel and Study Award Program, Schedule of Standard Allowances.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1-22 26 Sep 60 - 15 Nov 72 FF 38c, 1960, 1962, 1965, 1967-1972 (Box 27, Folder 9)
      Ford Foundation correspondents include: Edward F. D'Arms (Associate Director) re loan of Foundation books to Wayne; Joseph M. McDaniel, Jr. (Secretary) re cocktail party at Bob Mallary's for Elaine de Kooning, and death of Jules Harwood; William H. Nims (Assistant Secretary) re Tamarind catalogue, "The Tamarind Book of Lithography: Art & Techniques"; Kenneth W. Presscott (Program Officer) re Wayne's opinion on R. Joshua Young's Market Street Program in Venice, CA and copy of Tamarind's "A Guide to Print Terminology"; Libby Watterson (Photo Librarian, Office of Reports) re photographs of Tamarind Workshop for inclusion in Annual Report; other correspondents include William McPeak (Vice President); Henry T. Heald (President); Eugene S. Staples; Richard C. Sheldon; Susan de Armas; Oleg Lobanov; Nancy Boggs; and Felice Levin.
    - Thompson, Marcia 1-19, 1960, 1961, 1962, 1963, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 10)
      Marcia Thompson (Program Assistant, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: planning of Tamarind Lithography Workshop; preparing press releases for Tamarind grant announcement; U.S. Treasury Department's ruling on Tamarind's tax exemption status; photographs of Workshop for Foundation pictures files; feature story by Alfred M. Frankfurter on Tamarind for ArtNews; list of Tamarind artist fellows and guest artists (as of 1962); Tamarind progress report; W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) speaking at Pomona College symposium; Marcel Durassier's visit to New York.
    - Koch, Sigmund 1-1 22 Jun 64 - 27 Oct 66 Ford Foundation 38c, 1964, 1965, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 11)
      Sigmund Koch (professor of psychology, Duke University) re: becoming Director of Ford Foundation's Humanities and the Arts program; Guy Endore's book, "Satan's Saint" with lithographs by Robert Hansen (printer, Tamarind); problems with acquiring lithography paper; success of Rufino Tamayo lithography exhibition at Matisse Gallery, Los Angeles; Tamarind grant, cash flow; request for Wayne's nomination for Ford Foundation's Curatorial Training Program (1966); Wayne's speech on Foundation Gamesmanship given in San Francisco; cancellation of seminar for art dealers planned with Special Services to Business Industry Department, New York University (NYU); award of Tamarind Prize at Venice Biennale; advice on acquiring lithography stones; Wayne's dismissal of three fellow grantees (Erwin Erickson, Bob Bigelow, and Ian Lawson.)
    - Thompson, Marcia 1-18 2 Mar 65 - 22 Dec 67 FF 59c, 1956, 1959, 1962, 1964, 1965, 1966, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 12)
      Marcia Thompson (Program Assistant, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: Edward F. D'Arms' visit to Tamarind; Edward Kallop and collection at Department of Drawings and Prints, Cooper Union Museum, New York; marketing training seminar; Archives of American Art interest in micro-filming Tamarind documents; Foundation's flyer for 1966 Program for Administrative Interns, and Museum Curatorial Training Program; Wayne's participation with California State Arts Commission committees and possible conflict with Tamarind's tax exempt status; cancellation of seminar for art dealers planned with Special Services to Business Industry Department, New York University (NYU); award of Tamarind Prize at Venice Biennale; Wayne's speech on "The Art of Selling Art" at the National Association of Retail Merchants, New York; change to Tamarind's grant structure; Tamarind Annual Reports; acquiring lithographic stones and Wayne's "Operation Cornerstone"; Tamarind annual audits; also includes sample letters of Ford Foundation grants to California Institute of Technology (1956), Detroit Museum of Arts Founders Society (1959), Emery University Depart of Fine Arts (1962), fellowship to Kenneth Anger, film maker (1964), Inner City Cultural Center, Los Angeles (1967); Wayne's remarks about questionnaire from New York State Council on the Arts on Arts Administrator Job Potential in New York State.
    - Thompson, Marcia 1-17 29 Jan 68 - 13 Mar 72 FF 81c, 1968, 1969, 1970, 1971, 1972 (Box 27, Folder 13)
      Marcia Thompson (Program Assistant, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: Wayne's visit to New York and goal to find publisher for Tamarind textbook; Tamarind's "Management Study of an Art Gallery"; financial reports; Jim Woods and Watts Studio Workshop; returning Wayne's film for further editing; difficulties in program arrangements with Sterling Institute, (Harvard Business School); Tamarind exhibition at Ford Foundation; Barbara Koz and Sterling Institute; Wayne's response to prospectus on "A Book of Color Experiments" by Peter Gee; Wayne's response to Blackburn proposal; request for Wayne's nomination for Ford Foundation's Curatorial Training Program; Tamarind annual reports; request for sample letter for grant award; Tamarind exhibition catalogue; "Tamarind Book of Lithography: Art & Techniques"; Russell Lynes and lithographic presses for the MacDowell Colony; other correspondents include Nancy Boggs.
    - Lowry, McNeil 1- 9 2 Feb 65 - 16 Mar 65 FF 6c, 1965 (Box 27, Folder 14)
      W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: difficulty in acquiring lithography stones; also includes memo from Joseph M. McCaniel Jr. re Foundation Travel and Study Award Policy on Travel and Allowances for Wives and Children.
    - Goodman, Calvin, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      Calvin J. Goodman (Consulting Management & Industrial Engineer, Los Angeles) re Wayne's comments on Goodman's text, "Selling and Pricing the Artist's Work"; Goodman's "How to Avoid Synetropy: Preventing the Loss of Corporate Vitality after a Merger"; Contemporary Art Council's fund raising auction for the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (LACMA.)
    - Inter-Office Memos (Tamarind), 1966, 1967, 1968, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 6)
      Memorandums from Wayne to Tamarind staff and printers (1966 January 19-1970 January 29) re: no-smoking policy, meeting announcements, telephone usage, use of equipment, and theft of lithographic paper; signatures and initials appearing on memos include: Kinji Akagawa, Amy Baker, Dave Barajas, Bonnie Barrett, Robert Bigelow, Esther Bowers, John Butke, Ernest de Soto, Marsha Dexter, Bob Evermon, Betty Fiske, Dave Folkman, Manuel [Fuentes?], Fred Genis, Edward Hughes, Caren Jaseph, Don Kelley, Jack Lemon, Lillian Lesser, Serge Lozingot, Jean Milant, Norma Neiman, Glenn Oye, Judy Reilly, Robert Rogers, Maurice Sanchez, Jane Shelton, Clifford Smith, Anthony Stoeveken, Donna Tryon, Elin Waterman, Mary Webster, and Theo Wujcik.
    - Tamarind Institute 1980 (Box 37, Folder 6)
      Correspondents include: Clinton Adams (Director, Tamarind Institute) to Warrington Colescott (artist, author) re references to Tamarind Institute in Colescott's book, "A History of Printmaking: A Traveling Exhibition of the Madison Art Center, June 15-July 29, 1979"; Wayne to Duane Gilkey (attorney, Albuquerque, NM) re Wayne's recommendation of book by Karl Meyer, "The Art Museum: Power, Money, Ethics" (1979.)
    - Tamarind Institute 1981 (Box 37, Folder 7)
      Correspondents include: Hans-O. Wacker (Kunsthandel, Hannover, Germany) to John Sommers (Technical Director, Tamarind Institute) re offer of lithographic stones; Wayne to Clinton Adams (Director, Tamarind Institute) re archival papers and continuing litigation with Terry Sanders; Adams to Margaret Kaplan (Vice President and Executive Editor, Harry N. Abrams, Inc., New York, NY) re availability and agreement for publication of "The Tamarind Book of Lithography"; Adams to Wayne re Tamarind symposium, "Lithography Then and Now" (1981 November 15-16); Wayne to Adams re sale of John Merryman print collection; Kathy Zimmerer (Wayne's assistant) to Adams re sending boxes of Tamarind publications, correspondence files and financial data for the Tamarind Lithography Workshop Archives; Marge Bardacke (Assistant Director, Tamarind Institute; later known, as of 1981 December 3, as Marjorie Devon) re request for current retail values of lithographs printed by Wayne while at Tamarind, and announcement of publication of catalogue raisonné of Tamarind lithographs, 1970-1979; Peter S. Briggs (Registrar, University Art Museum, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM) re loan form for Wayne's prints; Don McRae (Dean of College of Fine Arts, University of New Mexico) re praise for the Tamarind Institute and Wayne's "The Dorothy Series"; also includes issue of "The Tamarind Institute Report" (Number 43 / 1981 December) and holiday postcard from Tamarind Institute.
    - Tamarind Institute 1982 (Box 37, Folder 8)
      Correspondents include: Marge (Bardacke) Devon re value of Wayne's Gorman lithographs, Wayne's Tamarind Collector's Club membership and Subscription Series, and Wayne's intent to sell some of her lithography stones; Phyllis Green (Wayne's assistant); Emily Kass (Assistant Director, University Art Museum, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM) and Peter S. Briggs (Registrar, University Art Museum) re Wayne's loan of work to exhibition, "Nine Contemporary Lithographers"; Clinton Adams to Garo Antreasian re publication of revised edition of "The Tamarind Book of Lithography"; Adams re his chapter for his book, "American Lithographers, 1900-1960."
    - Tamarind Institute 1983 (Box 37, Folder 9)
      Correspondents include: Clinton Adams (Director, Tamarind Institute) re Laurie Lisle (author) and book Lisle is writing on Louise Nevelson; Cappy Kuhn (Tamarind Institute) re arrival of lithography stones and her departure from Tamarind; Marjorie Devon (Assistant Director, Tamarind Institute) re restructuring of Tamarind Collector's Club subscription program; Adams and Duane C. Gilkey (attorney, Albuquerque, NM) re Wayne's litigation with Terry Sanders, the case's dismissal in Los Angeles Superior Court and settlement agreement.
    - Tamarind Institute 1984, 1983, 1984 (Box 38, Folder 1)
      Correspondents include: Marjorie Devon (Assistant Director, Tamarind Institute) to Robin Wayne re Tamarind Collector's Club membership renewal; Lynne Allen (Tamarind Institute) re graining machine given by Wayne to Tamarind Institute; Devon re response to request by Raymond Schuessler and Wayne's visit to New Mexico; Clinton Adams re Annual Report of Tamarind Institute (1983 June 1-1984 June 30); Adams to Donald McRae (Dean, College of Fine Arts, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM) re Adams' resignation as director of Tamarind Institute; Wayne to McAllister H. Hull, Jr. (Chairman, Office of the Provost, University of New Mexico) re Wayne's participation on search committee for Adams' replacement; also includes shipping invoice for graining machine and issue of "The Tamarind Papers: Technical, Critical and Historical Studies on the Art of the Lithograph" (Volume 7, Number 1, Spring 1984.)
    - Tamarind Institute 1985-1987, 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 38, Folder 2)
      Correspondents include: Marjorie Devon (Assistant Director, Tamarind Institute) re Artist Residency Proposal; Clinton Adams (Director, Tamarind Institute) to Tamarind Institute's National Advisory Board Members (Maurice Bloch, Paul Brach, Robert Gardner, W. McNeil Lowry, Anthony Stoeveken, Gustave von Groschwitz, June Wayne, and Ruth Weisberg) re Adams resignation as director, publication of journal, "The Tamarind Papers," establishment of an annual Tamarind citation for distinguished contributions to the art of the lithograph (presented to Gustave von Groschwitz), and exhibitions, "Tamarind: From Los Angeles to Albuquerque" at the Grunwald Graphic Arts Center at UCLA (1984 December 2), "Fifty Artists / Fifty Printers" organized by the University of New Mexico Art Museum for presentation during 1985 February symposium, an exhibition of 75 Tamarind lithographs to be circulated by the American Museum Association, 1985-1987, and project "México Nueve" scheduled for late 1986/early 1987; McAllister H. Hull, Jr. (Provost, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM) and Adams re appointment of Marjorie Devon as director of Tamarind (1985 June 21); Adams to W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re request for Lowry to serve on Tamarind Institute's National Advisory Board; Devon re her accomplishments thus far as director and award of National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) grant to catalogue Tamarind Lithography Workshop collection and publish catalogue raisonné (1985 December 12); Wayne to Devon re slides of Wayne's work and fact sheet; Katharine H. Downer re tour of Wayne's studio; Adams to Ed Hamilton re correspondence with Pat Gilmour and publishing a letter from Hamilton in next issue of The Tamarind Papers; Devon re Tamarind Annual Report (1986 July 1-1987 June 30) and funding problem; also includes list of search committee members (Clinton Adams, Vincent Beggs, Ruth Bowman, Marjorie Devon, Jerome A. Donson, Pat Gilmour, Michael Kurt, David Yager, Leonard Lehrer, W. McNeil Lowry, Joann Moser, Nina Parris, and Joan Shantz), Tamarind Institute lithography price lists (1985 June and December; 1986 June; 1987 March) and artists' biography sheets, exhibition checklist and announcement for "Tamarind: 25 Years 1960-1985" (1985 May18-August 30), and Gaikotsu Miyatake postcard from Linda Tyler (Assistant Editor, Tamarind Papers.)
    - Tamarind Institute 1988-1989, 1987, 1988 (Box 38, Folder 3)
      Correspondents include: Marjorie Devon (Director, Tamarind Institute) re address for Janet Sommers, extending Wayne's term on Tamarind advisory board, Tamarind Annual Report (1987 July 1-1988 June 30), Wayne's bout with influenza and pneumonia, and continuing litigation with Terry Sanders; Janet Sommers re the death of her husband, John Sommers (master printer and Technical Director, Tamarind Institute) (1988 January); also includes Tamarind Institute list of color slides of Tamarind lithographs, lithography price lists (1987 January; 1988 March and November), artists' biography sheets, and four-page computer printout list of names and address of printers and institutions.
    - Tamarind Institute 1989, 1988, 1989 (Box 38, Folder 4)
      Correspondents include: Marjorie Devon (Director, Tamarind Institute) re correspondence with Jorge de Sousa (l'atelier Point et Marge, Créteil, France); Patricia Savignac (Assistant to the Editor, Tamarind Institute) re publishing agreement between Wayne and the Tamarind Institute; Wayne's speech, "Broken Stones and Whooping cranes: Thoughts of a Willful Artist" given at the National Print Symposium of the Print Council of Australia (Australian National Gallery, Canberra, 1989 March 25); Wayne's request for video tapes of "Four Stones for Kanemitsu" to be sent to Hiroshima City Museum of Contemporary Art (Hiroshima, Japan); departure of Ed Hamilton from Wayne's studio (1989 June 5); invitation to Wayne from Mr. Shirakov, USSR Moscow Art Foundation, to exhibit her work; also includes Annual Report of Tamarind Institute (1988 July 1-1989 June 30), and Tamarind Institute lithography price list (1989 April) and artists' biography sheets.
    - Tamarind Institute 1990, 1989, 1990 (Box 38, Folder 5)
      Correspondents include: Marjorie Devon (Director, Tamarind Institute) re Wayne's speech, "Broken Stones and Whooping cranes: Thoughts of a Willful Artist" given at the National Print Symposium of the Print Council of Australia (Australian National Gallery, Canberra, 1989 March 25), with editorial revisions; Wayne's participation in Tamarind symposium and exhibition; Wayne's objections to her speech at symposium being taped; remodeling of Wayne's workshop building and sending box of books to Tamarind Institute (1990 September 6); Clinton Adams (Editor, Tamarind Papers journal) re publication of "Broken Stones" in Tamarind Papers; Linda P. Tyler (Assistant Editor, Tamarind Papers) re publishing agreement with Wayne; also includes Annual Reports of Tamarind Institute (1988 July 1-1989 June 30; 1989 July 1-1990 June 30), Tamarind Institute lithography price list (1989 April) and artists' biography sheets, and list of lithography stones (stored in Novaro, Italy) available for sale, loan or gift.
    - Tamarind Institute 1991, 1990, 1991, 1992 (Box 38, Folder 6)
      Correspondents include: Bill Lagattuta (printer, Tamarind Institute); Linda P. Tyler (Assistant Editor, Tamarind Papers) re Wayne's review of Ruth Weisberg's catalogue, "Ruth Weisberg Prints: Mid-life Catalogue Raisonné, 1961-1990" (Fresno Art Museum, June 1990); death of Joyce Treiman; Becky Schnelker (Curator, Tamarind Institute) re inadvertent bronzing noted in some prints; Wayne to Kyoko "Michi" Michishita re Wayne's work at Tamarind, publishing of Wayne catalogue by Pat Gilmour; also includes Annual Report of Tamarind Institute (1990 July 1-1991 June 30) and faxed document from Wayne to Marjorie Devon (Director, Tamarind Institute) re list of artists in Tamarind Suite XV.
    - Tamarind Institute 1992, 1991, 1992 (Box 38, Folder 7)
      Correspondents include: Bill Lagattuta (printer, Tamarind Institute) and Marjorie Devon (Director, Tamarind Institute) re reproofing two prints, "Eye Level" and "Inside Out"; Linda P. Tyler (Associate Editor, The Tamarind Papers) re complimentary copies of 1991-92 issues of Tamarind Papers and current retail values of Tamarind prints (1993); Becky Schnelker (Curator, Tamarind Institute) re Wayne's prints for exhibition; Devon re letter from Ko Muto; also includes Annual Report of Tamarind Institute (1991 July 1-1992 June 30.)
    - Tamarind Institute 1994 (Box 38, Folder 8)
      Correspondents include: Marjorie Devon (Director, Tamarind Institute) re her upcoming marriage to Tony Evanko; Becky Schnelker (Curator, Tamarind Institute) re book, "Hot Off the Press: Prints & Politics" edited by Linda Tyler and Barry Walker (University of New Mexico Press, c1994.)
    - Tamarind Institute- Subscription Correspondence, 1971, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1975 (Box 38, Folder 9)